Maximilian, Emperor of Mexico collection 1847-1967 (bulk 1853-1867)
University of Arizona Libraries, Special Collections
Maximilian, Emperor of Mexico collection 1847-1967 (bulk 1853-1867)
MS 108
Maximilian, Emperor of Mexico
Collection consists of documents, letters, and visual materials related to Emperor Maximilian, Empress Carlota, and the people associated with them in the European intervention in Mexico, 1861-1867.
2 linear feet
University of Arizona Libraries, Special Collections University of Arizona PO Box 210055 Tucson, AZ 85721-0055 Phone: 520-621-6423 Fax: 520-621-9733 URL: http://speccoll.library.arizona.edu/
Restrictions
None.
Biographical Note
Maximilian served as Emperor of Mexico from 1864-1867.
Organization
This collection is organized into four series:
Series I: Official Documents and Correspondence, 1853-1938
Series II: Letters, Itineraries, and Photographs of Maximilian and Carlota, 1847-1866
Series III: Letters, Documents, and Writings of Other Individuals, 1856-ca. 1907
Series IV: Ephemera, Photographs, and Broadsides, 1855-1967
Scope and Content Note
Collection consists of documents, letters, and visual materials related to Emperor Maximilian, Empress Carlota, and the people associated with them in the European intervention in Mexico, 1861-1867. Printed holographic imperial appointments and awards are signed by Maximilian, from 1864 to 1866. Other documents include letters and papers of Maximilian, Carlota, President Benito Juarez, and physicians Alvisio Miskey and Francisco Archer. Diaries and memoirs by others relate personal insights about the court and the political revolutions of the time. A diary by Charles Whitehead, mine owner and Mexico City resident, spans the years 1853 to 1865; an undated memoir "Les derniers jours de contre guerilla au Mexique" is by Jules de Rafelis-Saint-Sauveur; and a mimeographed copy of "My recollections of Maximilian" was written by Maria de la Fere, ca. 1907.
Printed documents include magazine and newspaper articles from Mexico, the U.S., and Europe, from 1867 to the centennial remembrance in 1967 of Maximilian's death. Broadsides, decrees by officials such as the interim Governor Rafael J. Garcia, campaign notices, and proclamations about the war encompass the period 1855-1867. An 1895 protest, signed by 126 students, concerns the traitor Leonard Marques being allowed to remain in Mexico. Among the visual materials are cartes-de-visite photographs, photographic postcards, and photogravure depictions of many civil and military individuals. Ephemera include color stills from the 1939 Warner Brothers movie "Juarez." Other items are drawings by H. D. Nichols from photographs, color prints of Mexican locations of historic interest, and a composite photo of the scene before Maximilian and two of his generals, Miguel Miramon and Tomas Mejia, were executed.
Collection is mostly in Spanish; some material is in French, German and English.
Maximilian, Emperor of Mexico, 1832-1867; Carlota, Empress, consort of Maximilian, Emperor of Mexico, 1840-1927; Juarez, Benito, 1806-1872; Mejia, Tomas, 1820-1867; Archer, Francisco; Garcia, Rafael J.; Miramon, Miguel, 1831-1867; Whitehead, Charles; Rafelis-Saint-Sauveur, Jules de; La Fere, Maria de; Miskey, Alvisio; Mexico -- History -- European intervention, 1861-1867 -- Sources; Mexico -- History -- 1821-1861 -- Photographs; Mexico -- Politics and government -- 1861-1867 -- Sources; Correspondence; Photographs; Photoprints; Diaries; Broadsides
Container List
- Series I: Official Documents and Correspondence, 1853-1938
  - Official document from Alaman dealing with the establishment of a Ministry of Public Works, Colonization, Industry and Commerce. (Mexico). April 27, 1853 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Alaman, President of the Republic, reminds government employees of their oath of office. (Mexico). April 28, 1853 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Adrian Woll to the Minister of the Interior: copy of a proclamation to the inhabitants of Carmargo as a result of an uprising lead by Jan Alvarez. (Carmargo). April 5, 1854 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - A decree issued by the substitute President of Mexico, Ignacio Comonfort, outlining a government subsidy for foreign commerce conducted in national (Mexican) ships. (Mexico). January 9, 1856 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Announcement that Concepcion Lombardo de Miramon is in residence at the National Palace of Chapultepec. (Chapultepec). May, 1859 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Zaragonza, Minister of War and Navy, issues a safeguard in the name of the President to Silvestre Alguin for the protection of the latter's property. (Mexico). August 24, 1861 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Emilio de Wagner, Minister of Prussia in Mexico, requests Mexican authorities for the safe conduct of transport vehicles from Mexico City to Vera Cruz and return, since they are transporting goods of subjects of a neutral foreign power. (Mexico). June 27, 1862 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Printed card from Eugenie to Madame Almonte. (In French). September, 1862 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - General Escobedo informs General Blanco, Minister of War, that Lt. Francisco Naranjo has been assigned to a reconnaissance unit and has left to report for duty, and that the division in Puebla is working on the fortifications which are expected to be completed by the 10th or 12th of November. (Puebla). October 29, 1862 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - General Mejia of the Imperial forces assures the inhabitants of Matamoros of complete guarantees for their lives and property. (Jacalitos). February 26, 1864 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Certificate in regard to loss of official papers during combat, from Miguel Miramon, General of the Division. (Guanajuato). March 10, 1864 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Telegram to Mr. Debranz, inviting him to dine at Miramar at 7 p.m. White tie. (In French). (Trieste). April, 1864 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Probably a copy or draft of what a member of the Mexican delegation said to Maximilian when he was offered the crown of Mexico at Miramar on April 10, 1864. (In French). April 10, 1864 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - A decree by Maximilian in regard to the Imperial coat of arms and the flags of Mexico. (Mexico). June 10, 1864 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Jose Blasio (Maximilian's private secretary) orders the Grand Master of Ceremonies to see His Majesty at 12 (noon?). (Mexico). February 21, 1865 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - A petition by Mexican citizens and creditors of the J. B. Jecker Company to approve arrangement made by the Minister of the Treasury to save the company from bankruptcy. (Mexico). April 8, 1865 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - William H. Seward, U. S. Secretary of State, thanks J. L. Polk for his letter of condolence upon the death of Seward's wife. (In English). (Washington, D.C.). July 24, 1865 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Chart of the seating arrangements for the Crown, the clergy, and other government officials at a mass celebrated in honor of Mexico. September 16, 1865 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Juan de Dios Peza, Minister of War, to the Emperor, informing him of the success of French troops in Durango, with a request that they not be withdrawn until they are replaced. (Mexico). February 6, 1866 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Moure to the editor of the journal La France. (In French, not translated.) (Mexico). February 10, 1866 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Leon Lewis Castellanos, correspondent for the (N.Y.?) Ledger, to the editor, Robert Bonner, regarding three articles he has written on the Mexican situation. Reports that he is about to be dispatched to Mexico "as a confidential agent of General Santa Anna." Encloses a part of a letter from Santa Anna. (In English). (Penn Yan, Yates County, N.Y.). June 28, 1866 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - General Ignacio Mejia to Silvestre Alguin. February 22, 1867 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Because of war conditions, the Emperor grants an extension of time to the Mexico and Tuxpan Railroad to complete certain work on the railroad without the payment of a fine. If, however, the work is not finished by the expiration of the new time, the Railroad will be subject to the penalty of the original agreement. Signed by Marquez. (Mexico). May 7, 1867 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Lerdo de Tejada to Carlos Maria Larranaga, requesting the restoration of rights to government employees which were deprived them during the Empire. (Mexico). January 17, 1868 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Senor Lerdo de Tejada appoints Vicente Cardenas as clerk of the 2nd section of the Department of the Interior. (Mexico). August 7, 1874 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Fernando Ramirez nominates Luis C. Curiel as interim chief clerk of the Department of Justice and Public Instruction. (Mexico). November 30, 1876 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Regarding the appointment of Luis C. Curiel (see above). December 1, 1876 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Empress Eugenie to Madame Almonte. Note of appreciation for the Madame's best wishes for the new year. (In French). (Florence). February 25, 1877 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Mariano Escobedo, the Mexican General to whom Maximilian surrendered, testifies that General of Brigade Fernando Toucel took part in the battle of Queretaro and conducted himself with bravery and honor. (Mexico). October 12, 1889 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Death certificate of Miguel Lopez (traitor). (Mexico). April 26, 1891 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Clothilde Almonte certifies that the attached Cross of San Carlos is that of the society founded in Mexico by Empress Carlota, and that the cross belonged to her grandmother, Dona Dolores Quesada de Almonte, First Lady of Honor at Carlota's court. (Cross missing). (In French). (Mexico). March 9, 1938 (Box 1, Folder 2)
- Series II: Letters, Itineraries, and Photographs of Maximilian and Carlota, 1847-1866
  - Maximilian to M. Dore, telling of the true manner in which someone died. (In French). (Schoenbrun). July 7, 1847 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Maximilian to Schaub, regarding name and purpose of the Institute of Marine Science. (In German). (Venice). May 18, 1858 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Maximilian regrets his inability to attend meeting of the Council because of naval business at Trieste. (In German). (Miramar). June 19, 1861 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Maximilian approves the major expense which is the distribution of prizes made in the present year to the students of the Academy and of Noble Arts of San Carlos. (Mexico). January 1, 1864 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Maximilian to "Baron", acknowledging letter asking for a meeting with Maximilian on the 22nd at Miramar. Will be "uncommonly" glad to see him, and hopes that he will telegraph him the moment he (the Baron) arrives. (In German). (Miramar). February 4, 1864 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Empress Carlota thanks Senora Almonte and through her the ladies of the Court for the gift of a dressing table. (Mexico). June 17, 1864 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Maximilian directs his Secretary of War to answer a letter from General Bazaine to the effect that in accordance with what he (Bazaine) proposes, the means which should be given to the protection of the Peninsula of Yucatan should be delayed, since the coast is guarded by French naval forces, and an estimate of the present situation should be made resulting in a definite decision. (Mexico). June 25, 1864 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Maximilian appoints Don Manuel Orozco y Berra as an Assistant Secretary in the Ministry of Public Works. (Mexico). November 15, 1864 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Maximilian to Baronin Sturmfeder, Lady-in-Waiting to Kaiserin Karoline Aguste von Osterreich. A friendly letter: "...Although very busy, I am feeling very well and enjoy myself in my position and in the beauty of the country. Charlotte blushes like a rose and has never been so cheerful... I would like you here with us..." With envelope addressed in the Emperor's hand. (In German). (Chapultepec). December 28, 1864 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Maximilian calls the attention of Minister Cortez y Esparza to an extensive report on government political problems and requests him to extract ones pertinent to his departure for study and recommendations for solution. (Chapultepec). January 5, 1865 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Maximilian to Dr. Jilek, regarding general conditions in Mexico. (In German). (Chapultepec). February 10, 1865 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Maximilian to Siliceo, acknowledging letter of the 27th regarding the "gossip and intrigue" which is current from Rome and Washington. However, he is not frightened and remains firm on the path he has taken. Minister Siliceo has his confidence and gratitude. "The only deed that I deplore is that circumstances do not permit us to even explain the energy and swiftness that is necessary for the good service to the Nation." (Pachuca). August 29, 1865 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Empress Carlota to Senora Almonte in Mexico City. A telegram stating she heard of the illness of the latter's husband and asking about his present condition. She states that she herself is very well. (Vera Cruz). October 21, 1865 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Maximilian gives detailed instructions to his Master of Ceremonies. (Mexico). December 9, 1865 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Telegram from Maximilian to the Minister of Government: "I will give you orders in order that the Imperial visitor Garcia will arrange as soon as possible with Count Thun that I await him with anxiety as a result of the latest success of the Austrian troops. Misantla is already occupied by our troops." (Chapultepec). December 24, 1865 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Maximilian thanks Minister Estera for the latter's expression of condolence up the death of King Leopold of Belgium. (Chapultepec). January 19, 1866 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Maximilian grants permission to General Juan N. Almonte to accept decorations conferred by the Kings of Belgium and Spain. (Mexico). March 12, 1866 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Royal Itinerary of trip from Vera Cruz to Puebla. December 23-27, (year?) (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Royal Itinerary of the Empress on her visit to Merida. Also general instructions for the retinue (division of the cavalcade, positions of various persons dress), Greetings of the Empress to the people on arrival, dance program in her honor, playbill for "Isabel the Catholic" (dedicated to the Empress), printed expressions of gratitude from the people, and copies of newspapers reporting on the visit. November, 1865 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Maximilian: Photographs (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Carlota: Photographs (Box 1, Folder 6)
- Series III: Letters, Documents, and Writings of Other Individuals, 1856-ca. 1907
  - Benito Juarez Letters and Documents, 1856-1865
    - Juarez acknowledges the receipt of a government document and states he will answer as soon as possible. (Oaxaca). July 10, 1856 (Box 1, Folder 7)
    - Certificate of gratitude to Lt. Juan Ramirez, Infantry, for his conduct on the 5th of May, 1862, in Puebla. (Mexico). May 30, 1862 (Box 1, Folder 7)
    - Juarez to General Miguel Vignese, regarding military operations against the Empire in Durango. (Chihuahua). March 14, 1865 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Dr. Alvisio Miskey Letters and Documents, 1865-1867
    - Dr. Jilek to "Friend" (Dr. Miskey?), regarding a letter from this friend and showing it to the Empress. (In German). (Vienna). April 18, 1865 (Box 1, Folder 8)
    - Dr. Miskey is made physician of the Imperial Court. Signed by Almonte. (Mexico). August 1, 1865 (Box 1, Folder 8)
    - Maximilian makes Dr. Miskey a caballero of the Imperial Order of Guadalupe. (Mexico). December 26, 1865 (Box 1, Folder 8)
    - Certification of Dr. Miskey's promotion to Captain, 2nd class, in the Medical Corps of the Austro-Mexican volunteers in 1865. Signed by the Minister of War. (Mexico). April 10, 1866 (Box 1, Folder 8)
    - Furlough certificate of Dr. Miskey. (Puebla). May 14, 1866 (Box 1, Folder 8)
    - Unidentified correspondent to "Friend" (Dr. Miskey?), regarding fast trip from Mexico to Trieste. (In German). (Vienna). July 27, 1866 (Box 1, Folder 8)
    - Printed program of a concert by the Societe Philharmonique de Bruxelles. (In French). (Bruxelles). July 13, 1866 (Box 1, Folder 8)
    - Frau Wuha (?) to Dr. Miskey, regarding a prescription. (In German). (Miramar). August 11, 1866 (Box 1, Folder 8)
    - Dr. Miskey is made a chevalier of the Order of Leopold. Accompanied by official certificate, dated July 20, 1866. (In French). (Burxelles). September 3, 1866 (Box 1, Folder 8)
    - Frau Wuha (?) to Dr. Miskey, regarding a prescription. (In German). (Miramar). October 26, 1866 (Box 1, Folder 8)
    - Dr. Jilek to Dr. Miskey, regarding Empress Carlota's concern over the health of Vice-Admiral von Tegelhof. (In German). (Miramar). November 7, 1866 (Box 1, Folder 8)
    - Frau Wuha (?) to Dr. Miskey, concerning general affairs at the palace. (In German). (Mexico). December 27, 1866 (Box 1, Folder 8)
    - Award of Order of Leopold Medal to Dr. Miskey. (In German). (Graz). January 13, 1867 (Box 1, Folder 8)
    - Discharge paper of Dr. Miskey from Mexican service. (In German). (Orizaba). February 24, 1867 (Box 1, Folder 8)
    - Unidentified corresponent (but same handwriting as Frau Wuha ?) to Dr. Miskey, regarding crate of goods from Mexico and court affairs. (In German). (Miramar). April 17, 1867 (Box 1, Folder 8)
    - Dr. Dietrich to Dr. Miskey, mainly about personal affairs. (In German). (Altona). October 25, 1867 (Box 1, Folder 8)
    - Musical program. Trieste? (In German). No Date (Box 1, Folder 8)
    - Notes of Dr. Miskey. (In German). No Date (Box 1, Folder 8)
    - Request for medical excuse to a military order. (In German). No Date (Box 1, Folder 8)
    - Description of a painting of Maximilian astride a horse, by Ebersberg. (In German). No Date (Box 1, Folder 8)
    - List of rare items from Mexico -- apparently packed in crates and cases, and shipped from there to Dr. Alais Edlen at Graz, Austria. (In German). No Date (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Dr. Francisco Archer Letters and Documents, 1857-1866
    - Immigration paper, Bordeaux, France, to Buenos Aires, Argentina. (In French). (Bordeaux). July 24, 1857 (Box 1, Folder 9)
    - Letter enclosing a decree appointing Dr. Archer as surgeon of the line of the frontier on the Chaco. (Parana). October 18, 1858 (Box 1, Folder 9)
    - A General Order of the General Headquarters on the Chaco, promoting Surgeon 2nd Class Archer to Surgeon 1st Class. (Parana). March 25, 1860 (Box 1, Folder 9)
    - By order of the President of the Republic of Argentina, Dr. Archer is assigned as surgeon aboard (unidentified) ship. (Rosario). October 5, 1861 (Box 1, Folder 9)
    - Letter enclosing a decree granting Dr. Archer a six-months sick leave because of ill health. (Parana). November 30, 1864 (Box 1, Folder 9)
    - Appointment of Dr. Archer as titular physician of the Province of Jujuy, Argentina. Accompanied by statement of his duties in this position. (Jujuy). March 30, 1865 (Box 1, Folder 9)
    - Acceptance of the resignation of Dr. Archer as the titular physician of Jujuy. (Jujuy). August 8, 1865 (Box 1, Folder 9)
    - American and Mexican Steamship Co. dinner menu. (In English). June 8, 1866 (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Charles Whitehead Diary, February, 1853-April, 1856
    - Resident of Mexico City, apparently the owner of mines in Veta Grande and Comanja. Chiefly a personal diary, but includes notes and experiences of the many political revolutions of the years 1853-1865. (In English). February, 1853-April, 1856 (Box 1, Folder 10)
- Series IV: Articles, Ephemera, Photographs, and Broadsides, 1855-1967
  - Jules de Rafelis-Saint-Sauver: "Les Derniers Jours de la Contre Guerilla au Mexique." 18--? (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - Maria de la Fere: "My Recollections of Maximilian." 1907? (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - Henry C. Clarke: "A Day's Fighting in Queretaro." ( Harper's). (In English). 1868 (Box 1, Folder 13)
  - John Heard, Jr.: "Maximilian and Mexico." ( Scribner's Magazine). (In English). June 1894 (Box 1, Folder 13)
  - Galleys of "Le Statut Provisoire de l'Empire Mexicain." (In French). (Box 1, Folder 14)
  - Menu of a party given by Empress Carlota on her birthday. June 4, 1866 (Box 1, Folder 14)
  - Poetic tributes to Maximilian. (Box 1, Folder 14)
  - Pictures of civil and military medals for merit (Imperio Mexicano). 1863 (Box 1, Folder 14)
  - Photocopy of a notice to emigrants: "The Forns' Colony," regarding land offered for settlement on the Panuco River, Tamaulipas, Mexico. (In English). February 6, 1866 (Box 1, Folder 14)
  - Card of Dr. v. Basch, physician to Maximilian. (Inscribed in German). (Box 1, Folder 14)
  - Models (standards) of stationery paper and stamps ordered to be used in accordance with the Circular of November 1, 1865. (Box 1, Folder 14)
  - Eight photographs from the movie, "Juarez," starring Paul Muni, Bette Davis, Brian Aherne. (Box 1, Folder 15)
  - Musical score, "Poor Carlotta!" Words by Paulina, music by F. W. Root. Chicago. 1867 (Box 1, Folder 15)
  - Issue of Point West, containing excerpt from play by Tim Kelly, Song of the Dove. (In English). February, 1964 (Box 1, Folder 15)
  - Photographs of Events in the Life of Maximilian. (Box 2, Folder 1)
  - Photographs of Trieste and Miramar. (Box 2, Folder 2)
  - Photographs of the Trial and Execution of Maximilian, and Generals Mejia and Miramon. (Box 2, Folder 3)
  - Photographs of Chapultepec and Museum Pieces. (Box 2, Folder 4)
  - Photographs of Mexico: Miscellaneous Places and Battles. (Box 2, Folder 5)
  - Photographs of Benito Juarez. (Box 2, Folder 6)
  - Photographs of Persons, A-Z. (Box 2, Folder 7-11)
  - Photographs of Persons (Miscellaneous, mostly small photographs). (Box 2, Folder 12)
  - Photographs of Clergy (small photographs only). (Box 2, Folder 13)
  - Military Photographs (small photographs only). (Box 2, Folder 14)
  - "Maximilian's Movement." Original drawing by H. D. Nichols. (Box 3)
  - "The Calvary of Queretara." Original drawing by H. D. Nichols. (Box 3)
  - Broadside (Mexico). June 20, 1855 (Box 3)
    Decree by Antonio Lopez de Santa-Anna conferring the cross of Knight of the National and Distinguished Mexican Order of Guadalupe upon Pedro Rafael Conejo.
  - Broadside (Mexico). May 1, 1858 (Box 3)
    "Miguel Maria Azcarate, Retired Colonel and Governor of the District of Mexico to the inhabitants, know ye:
    That through the Minister of Justice, Ecclesiastical Affairs and Public Instruction, the following has been addressed to me. His Excellency, Felix Zuloaga, the President pro tem of the Republic, issues an order consisting of twenty-nine articles.
    Article 1. Those who rob on the roads or uninhabitated sections and those who rob with violence or make forced entry in any way to houses, and the accomplices of those, will be judged by a regular council of war.
    Article 2. In the cities where the General Commanders reside and in any place where there are Captains in sufficient number -4 of these and a chief will form the War Board to judge the prisoners mentioned.
    Article 3. The Board will consult with the Counselor from the Juridical Body of the Military where there is one and, where there is not, with the Judges of the Criminal and Civil Courts who will serve alternately, and if there are no Judges in the place, the Board will consult with any lawyer who is in the place where the Board meets or in the nearest place thereto." (Trans. The remaining articles de la with the manner and terms in which justice shall be meted out.
  - Broadside (Puebla). January 21, 1861 (Box 3)